Ellery C. Stowell Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ellery C. Stowell Papers 1805-1952 (bulk 1880-1952)
MSS41681
Stowell, Ellery C. (Ellery Cory), 1875-1958
14,000 items
49 containers plus 1 oversize
19.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Author, jurist, and professor of international law. Family correspondence, general correspondence, diaries, writings, reports, sermons, notebooks, financial records, printed matter, scrapbooks, photographs, and other papers relating primarily to Stowell's career in law, activities as a student, and travels. Includes papers of the Stowell, Fuller, and Tapley families.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Fuller family.; Stovall family.; Stowell, Ellery C. (Ellery Cory), 1875-1958.; Tapley family.
Organizations
American University (Washington, D.C.)--Faculty.; American University (Washington, D.C.). Hall of Nations.; Better Government League (Washington, D.C.); Columbia University--Faculty.; George Washington University--Faculty.; Harvard University--Students.; International Naval Conference (1908-1909: London, England); International Peace Conference (2nd: 1907: Hague, Netherlands); Patriotic Service League (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects
Academic freedom.; Disarmament.; International law--Study and teaching.; International law.; Peace--Congresses.; Political participation--United States.; Universities and colleges--France--Paris.; Universities and colleges--Germany--Berlin.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.
Places
America--Description and travel.; Asia--Description and travel.; Europe--Description and travel.
Occupations
Authors.; Educators.; Jurists.
Provenance
The papers of Ellery C. Stowell, author, jurist, and professor of international law, were given to the Library of Congress by Stowell, 1943-1949, and by Hevlyn Dirck Benson, 1943. Foundling material was added to the collection in 1976.
Transfers
Five photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ellery C. Stowell are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1875, Dec. 12 Born, Lynn, Mass.
1898 A.B. Harvard University, Cambridge, Md.
1901 1902 Traveled in Asia and Europe
1902 1903 Traveled in Russia
1903 1904 Attended University of Berlin, Berlin, Germany
1904 1907 Attended University of Paris, Paris, France
1906 Earned French law degree
1906 Graduate, Diplomatic Section, Ecole libre des sciences politiques, Paris, France
1907 Secretary adjoint, Second International Peace Conference, Hague, Netherlands, and also secretary of the Panama delegation
1908 1909 Secretary, American delegation, International Naval Conference, London, England
1908 1910 Instructor in international law, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1909 Became doctor of laws
1910 1913 Assistant professor in international law, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pa.
1912 Married Cecile M. Roberts
1913 1914 Lecturer in international law, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1914 1916 Associate professor in international Law, Columbia University, New York, N.Y.
1922 Professor in international law, American University, Washington, D.C.
1935 President, Better Government League, Washington, D.C.
1935 1944 Chairman, Department of International Affairs
1942 1943 Exchange professor, University of Washington, Seattle, Wash.
1958, Jan. Died, San Francisco, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ellery C. Stowell (1875-1958) span the years 1805-1952, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1880-1952. The collection includes his own papers as well as other members of the Stowell, Fuller, and Tapley families. It consists of family correspondence, general correspondence, reports, writings, sermons, diaries, notebooks, certificates, photographs, financial records, printed matter, scrapbooks, and miscellaneous material. The papers are organized into five series: Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Subject File, Miscellany, and Oversize.
Topics relate to Stowell's activities as a student at Harvard University and the universities of Paris and Berlin; his extensive travels in Europe, Asia, and America; and his work as a professor of international law at George Washington University, Columbia University, American University, and other institutions, particularly with respect to academic freedom at Columbia and the administration of the graduate school of American University in connection with the program of the Hall of Nations. Other subjects concern his efforts as president of the Better Government League and work with the Patriotic Service League and other civic organizations. Additional material relates to his activities as secretary adjoint of the International Peace Conference at the Hague in 1907, secretary of the Panama delegation to the same conference, and secretary of the American delegation to the International Naval Conference in London of 1908-1909. The collection also contains his writings on World War I and World II and their aftermath.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Family Correspondence, 1805-1952
General Correspondence, 1872-1949
Subject File
Miscellany
Oversize
Container List
- Family Correspondence, 1805-1952 (Box 1-12)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged by accession and mostly in chronological order therein.
  - Accession 7,316 (Box 1)
    - 1805-1883 (Box 1)
    - 1884-1917 (Box 2)
    - 1918-1930 (Box 3)
    - 1931-1935 (Box 4)
    - 1936-1940, undated (Box 5)
    - Fuller family genealogy (Box 5)
    - Letters collected by A. T. Stowell, 1884-1905 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous notes of Mrs. George L. Stowell (Box 5)
  - Accession 7,323 (Box 6)
    - 1871-1923 (Box 6)
    - 1920-1932 (Box 7)
    - 1938-1943 (Box 8)
  - Accession 7,532 (Box 9)
    - 1875-1906 (Box 9)
    - 1907-1914 (Box 10)
  - Accession 7,533 (Box 11)
    - 1846-1925 (Box 11)
  - Various accessions (Box 12)
- General Correspondence, 1872-1949 (Box 13-25)
  Letters sent received.
  Arranged by accession and therein chronologically.
  - Accession 7,316 (Box 13)
    - 1882-1913 (Box 13)
    - 1914-1918 (Box 14)
    - 1919-1926 (Box 15)
    - 1927-1931 (Box 16)
    - 1932-1944 (Box 17)
  - Accession 7,323 (Box 18)
    - 1914-1928 (Box 18)
    - 1926-1937 (Box 19)
  - Accession 7,533 (Box 20)
    - 1926-1943 (Box 20)
  - Accession 8,184 (Box 21)
    - 1872-1912 (Box 21)
    - 1913-1945 (Box 22)
  - Accession 9,317 (Box 23)
    - 1902-1909 (Box 23)
    - 1910-1917 (Box 24)
    - 1918-1949, undated (Box 25)
- Subject File (Box 36-31)
  Correspondence, writings, poems, sermons, notes, reports, printed matter, and other material.
  Arranged by name of organization, subject, or type of material.
  - Armed merchantmen, correspondence and notes, 1919 (Box 26)
  - Better Government League, correspondence, 1818-1828 (Box 27)
  - Patriotic Service League, correspondence, 1917-1918, 1943 (Box 28)
  - Mach, Edmund von, "Official Diplomatic Documents Relating to the Outbreak of the War," correspondence and notes by Stowell reading the book, 1911-1940 (Box 29)
  - American University Graduate School, Washington, D.C. (Box 29)
  - Panama, 1911-1913 (Box 29)
  - Academic Freedom, Columbia University, New York, N.Y. (Box 29)
  - Notes and speeches (Box 29)
  - Hague Conference (Box 30)
  - International Law (Box 30)
  - Reorganization of the State Department (Box 30)
  - Sermons of George L. Stowell (Box 31)
  - Poems copied by George L. Stowell (Box 31)
- Miscellany (Box 32-49)
  Cards, indexes, circulars, notebooks, diaries and cash books of family members, clippings, books, printed matter, scrapbooks, photographs, certificates, and miscellaneous documents and items.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Notebooks of Addie T. Fuller (Mrs. George L. Stowell) (Box 32)
  - Cards and badges (Box 32)
  - Certificates and photographs See Oversize (Box 32)
  - Circulars (Box 32)
  - Notebooks, diaries and scrapbooks of George L. Stowell (Box 33)
  - Newspaper articles (Box 34)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 34)
  - Clippings (Box 34)
  - Intervention in international law, books with two letters inserted (Box 35)
  - Lecture notebook on international law, in German (Box 35)
  - Cash books (Box 35)
  - Clippings (Box 36)
  - Clippings (Box 37)
  - Card index (Box 38)
  - Cash book of George L. Stowell, 1890-1898 (Box 39)
  - Scrapbooks containing letters, autographs, telegrams, other documents, printed matter, and clippings (Box 40-49)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  Certificates and photographs.
  Described according to the series and container from which the items were removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Certificates and photographs (Container 32) (Box OV 1)